<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A compendious treatise entituled, De re militari containing principall orders to be obserued in martiall affaires. VVritten in the Spanish tongue, by that worthie and famous captaine, Luis Gutierres de la Vega, citizen of Medina del Campo. And newlie translated into English, by Nicholas Lichefild.</title>
            <title>De re militari. English</title>
            <author>Gutierrez de la Vega, Luis, b. ca. 1509.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103562</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839313</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839313</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3721</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02408)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3721)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 320:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A compendious treatise entituled, De re militari containing principall orders to be obserued in martiall affaires. VVritten in the Spanish tongue, by that worthie and famous captaine, Luis Gutierres de la Vega, citizen of Medina del Campo. And newlie translated into English, by Nicholas Lichefild.</title>
                  <title>De re militari. English</title>
                  <author>Gutierrez de la Vega, Luis, b. ca. 1509.</author>
                  <author>Lichefield, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas East,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Ianuarij primus. 1582. Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1582]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A2 is a cancel.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part 2 of: Styward, Thomas.  1582. Januarii decimus. The pathwaie to martiall discipline: London, [1582].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3721:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3721:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A COMPENDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Treatiſe entituled, De re militari, containing principall orders to be obſerued in Martiall affaires.</p>
            <p>Written in the Spaniſh tongue, by that worthie and famous Captaine, Luis Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tierres de la vega, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of Medina del Campo.</p>
            <p>AND NEWLIE TRANS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into Engliſh, by Nicholas Lichefild.</p>
            <p>Ianuarij primus. 158<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>¶Imprinted at London by Thomas Eaſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3721:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3721:2"/>
            <head>¶To the right Worshipfull <hi>Maiſter Philip Syd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS little Treatiſe (Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) entituled, De re militari: beeing lately found in the Forte in Irelande, where the Italians and Spaniards had fortified theſemlues, by fortune came vnto wy hands by a souldier of good experience, who latly ſerued there: which after I had peruſed (&amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuiſe of ſome of better vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding then my ſelfe in thoſe affaires, which very much liked and allowed the worke) I was greatly boldned &amp; encouraged to enterpriſe the Tranſlation of the ſame, partly becauſe theſe principall orders are alwaies to bee obſerued in warlike gouernement, and chifely becauſe in our Engliſh tongue, I finde not the lyke extant, for the neceſſary inſtruction and generall commoditie of our common Souldiers: which briefe introduction (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing common in our language) may be an inducement to betrer knowledge, and further vnderſtanding, wherby in time our ſeruitours by good obſeruaunce and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, may attaine the lyke perfection, that all other forreine Nations doe generally embrace. And finding not any more forward then your Worſhip, to further and fauour this Martiall knowledge (beeing of your ſelfe moſt ready &amp; aduenterous in all exerciſes of feats of warre and chiualry) I haue therfore preſumed (as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen) to dedicate this briefe worke vnto you, which as a ſimple token of my good will, I doe humbly pray you to accept in good part, not doubting but that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your protection the ſame ſhall be ſufficientlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb facs="tcp:3721:3"/>
and well lyked, and thoſe imperfections in mee the Tranſlator, the better borne withall, wherin I haue rather obſerued the true and litterall ſence, then anye waies varied from the order of the matter, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour ſetteth it forth. And euen ſo referring my ſelfe and ſlender trauell vnto your curteous acceptation, wiſhing you that increaſe of worſhip and proſperitie, as euery wayes your noble minde deſerueth, doe euen ſo take my leaue. From Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the .9. of December. 1581.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie to commaund, <hi>Nicholas Lichfild.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:3721:3"/>
            <head>¶The prologue of the Authour to the Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y olde and féeble age which now hath fully atteined the number of lx yeares, with the ſundry requeſts of many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men my very friends, which many times haue giuen me occaſion to yéelde héerevnto, moueth me now (my fatall, vncerteine end approching) to ſatiſfie &amp; accompliſh theyr reaſonable deſire, and therefore I haue now enterpriſed to ſhew them in a ſmall treatiſe, by noting, that which many times they haue intreated me by word of mouth, a matter that hath bene thought by them I could better performe (then in truth I am able) by reaſon of the long continuance that in the art <hi>De re militari,</hi> my troubles and trauell hath brought me vnto. And although y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſome haue written of this matter héeretofore very excellently (with great perfection,) yet for that thoſe times and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice the which they did write of, doth differ much from that which is at this preſent. It cannot be, but this my trauell (at leaſtwiſe if it deſerue to be called trauell) will ſomewhat profit them, which truly I haue taken in hand but onely for pleaſure and recreation. And foraſmuch as that which is already written of this matter, is but of a few authours, which were well knowne, &amp; if there were many more, yet it cannot be ordered by their rules &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts without great inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience, for truly in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there would be great want within our time, if there were no order by art for to place in proportion, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer number be it great or ſmal, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ought to be eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; more chiefly obſerued, then thoſe rules which bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth &amp; compelleth with preſcription of number by limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and marke appointed them as though that there they ſhould end, which is to be amplified and increaſed vnto ſuch a greatneſſe as the number doth require, and this may be ſpoken of many, that I doe it of a new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention,
<pb facs="tcp:3721:4"/>
if there were not many others that reade this little treatiſe, which will affirme themſelues to knowe the ſame, the which giueth me occaſion not to offer this my rude worke vnto ſuch, but vnto thoſe vnſkilfull ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers as are not inſtructed in the art of ordering, or haue any light or knowledge what they ought to doe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnto ſuche as are moſt excellent Maiſters and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, there is no order but that they haue perfect, no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice but they haue ſéene, no warres but that they haue béene in, nor no other ſcience but that they doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. Vnto ſuch therfore the whole iudgement ought to be left, foraſmuch as Fortune and Nature hath endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with ſo great value, whereby they deſerue to be more aduaunced then thoſe hoarie heads of lx. yeares of experience, vnto whome hath all things bene contrarye, for not allowing or hauing any regard vnto ſtraunge things, but eſtéeming more their owne proper dooings, whoſe knowledge cannot be leſſe then this that I ſette forth.</p>
            <p>I doe not meane to publiſh this to ſuch like perſons of vnderſtanding, but rather I doe requeſt them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe me of my ignoraunce, for that the ſame maye bée amended &amp; corrected that is amiſſe. And alſo I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them if there be anye thing in this which before was vnknowne vnto them, that they woulde in good part friendlye accepte the ſame at their diſcreations, for my intent is onelye to write vnto thoſe that are affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned vnto matters of the warre, and to the arte of ordering, not deſirous to ſtaye vppon a long experience to ſée the ſame done, without there be an order to helpe them, or art to make them perfect, to ſuch I doe pray, deſire, and earneſtly requeſt, that they do not deſiſt from ſo worthy an intent, ſince that order that we doe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallye ſet foorth and declare, is ſo meruailous and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull.</p>
            <p>For by the ſame we doe ſée the daye and night is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned,
<pb facs="tcp:3721:4"/>
by this the bodylye health of man is preſerued, all Cities and Townes well ordered and mainteined, and by the ſame, Kingdomes are ſuſteyned, vpholden, and kepte in peace, and the people in quietneſſe and tranquilitye, the which order in matters of warre, they ought to haue in lyke regarde as in that of a Citye, that is well gouerned, yea, farre better, for in one onely Citye, the hurt or loſſe of ill gouernement is therein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed, but the lacke of order in a Campe or Armye of men in time of neceſſitye and approch of enimyes, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes hath béen the onely loſſe of ſundrie kingdomes. The which béeing knowne vnto the Maieſtye of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to thoſe that doth gouerne in theyr high Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells of warre, hath beſtowed ſuch offices vppon ſuche excellent graue perſons of vnderſtanding, to whome they may moſt aſſuredlye commit and giue all care &amp; charge thereof, leauing the ſame to theyr moſt prudent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>I doe leaue to ſpeake of thoſe excellent Generalles, the which are at this preſent, whoſe prayſe I dare not with my pen to touch, but rather referre that to others, who canne better ſette foorth theyr worthye commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and it is ſufficient for me to bée thankfull that GOD hath giuen vs them from aboue, for the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the earth.</p>
            <p>And thus thou godlye Reader which art affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned vnto this arte of a Souldyer, doe not giue ouer, nor ceaſe not to procéede in this manly enterpriſe and pretence, for by the ſame thou ſhalt reape moſt ſwéete and delectable pleaſure and rewarde, that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thée, and beſides ſhalt lyue in an exerciſe, that is greatlye eſtéemed, from whence thou ſhalt obtayne honour, which is thy laſt deſire. And nowe firſt you muſt vnderſtande, that it is neceſſarye to abandonne all ſuche faultes, as are accuſtomed to bée, at the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of a Companye, of whoſe diſorder commonlye
<pb facs="tcp:3721:5"/>
chaunceth great daungers and inconueniences, becauſe the Captaines haue not commonly that great reſpect and care to the charge that doth apperteine vnto them. And therefore I will declare how they ſhall march and bée gouerned, &amp; of their obedience to the order, the which is giuen them by theyr Officers, the which ſhall bée diuided into thrée partes, beginning after the order following.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3721:5"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>¶THE FIRST PART, <hi>De re militari.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶Of the order which ought to be obſerued, in the marching forward of a company of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, from the place where they are lodged. Cap. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for marching from the alodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from whence a Captaine with his companie are in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to departe, this order muſt bée obſerued. Firſt, the Captaine muſt cauſe to proclaime, that all ſuch Souldiers which are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to ſerue vnder the Enſigne and gouernment of ſuch a Captaine, prepare themſelues to be in readineſſe, with their armour and furniture the next daye following in the morning, which vſually is at the dawning of the daye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe the companye maye march forward a reaſonable iourney.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How ſuch a company of ſouldiers, ſhould bee prouided with furniture neceſſary. Cap. 2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He night before their departure, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant of the Band, by commaundement from his Captaine or Lieuetenant hath to deale with the Rulers of the Citie, Towne or Village where they are lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that they prepare ſuch neceſſarye Baggage as the companie ſhall want. In the prouiſion of which furniture, the Corporall of euery Squadron, ſhall make enquirie among his company of their preſent want, and then to kéepe an account or reckoning, what
<pb facs="tcp:3721:6"/>
is deliuered ouer and beſide the neceſſaries, deliuered to the Captaine or his Lieuetenaunt.</p>
                  <p>The which prouiſion ſhall be brought to a place or houſe in the Towne, and there perticular repetition to be made, in ſuch ſort, that no Officer take without order, more then iuſtly doth appertaine vnto them, and that equally to be deuided vnto euerie Squadron. A Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron properly is the number of xxv. men, of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber each Corporall hath charge, and euerie vnder Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſhall haue the like charge of ſuch numbers, as ſhal be committed vnto them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How the Souldiers ſhall ioyne or come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in what order. Cap. 3.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the morning after repertition of their Baggage, whileſt the Souldiers prepare themſelues for their departure, the drum player ought to repaire to their Enſigns, to the houſe of the Auncient Bearer, which is the place of méeting. And then the Sergeant of the Band, as his Souldiers repaire and come together, ſhall march in a rounde or Muſter to ſée if any want, and dayly to accuſtome themſelues to attend vpon their Enſigne or Aunntient.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶Of the order and manner how they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the place where they were lodged. Cap. 4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the greateſt part of the companye are ioyned, the Enſigne ſhall march out of the Towne or lodgement with the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in good order, and when they are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a reaſonable ſpace from the Towne, they ſhall there ſtaye. And the Sergeant
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3721:6"/>
of the Band ſhall retourne backe againe to the Towne, to ſée if any of his companye remaine behinde, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any, to compel them to followe and repaire to theyr Enſigne, and to rebuke or reprehend them for their delay and ſlackneſſe: in ſuch wiſe that they may vnderſtande, that they ought to be in ſubiection to theyr Princes Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How the Baggage muſt paſſe, when the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye is commaunded to march forwarde. Cap. 5.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Officers hath to commaund y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to be placed in the Vangard, before the Enſigne. This is to be vnderſtoode, where there are no enimies. But where the enimie is expected, there ſhall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage be placed either in the Vangarde or Reregard at the diſcretion of the Officers. But if it happen to be appointed in the Vangard it ſhal goe about the length of a Croſſebowe ſhot, before the companye, ſo that alwayes they kéepe in their ſight for the ſauegarde of the cariage. Prouided alwayes, that one Squadron, of Hargubuſiers, or Pike men ſhall goe ioyntly in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the baggage, as by daily lot ought to be appointed for that purpoſe, &amp; the officer that hath the charge of the Squadron, which commonly is called <hi>Cabo de Squadra,</hi> ſhall haue reſpect when the Enſigne doth ſtay which is meant onely to tarry for ſuch Souldiers as come drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging behinde with wearineſſe in the Reregard. The lyke muſt be done with them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath the charge of the baggage. And then ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany begin to march they then ought to march alſo, vntil they come to their alodgment. But before the company ouertake them, they ſhall ſtaye &amp; abide with their baggage about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> length of .2. or .3. ſhot of a Croſſebow, before they come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appointed place of
<pb facs="tcp:3721:7"/>
lodging, to be aduertiſed in what part of the Towne, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or Village, they ſhall enter, following their Enſigne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How, and in what order they ſhall enter to the alodgement. Cap. 6.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S ſoone as the maine company are come to the place where the baggage abideth their comming, all ſuch Souldiers that haue Horſes, ſhall alyght from their horſes, and accompany their Enſigne, entering into the Towne in good order. The Captaine ought to haue ſpeciall care that none of his companye preſume to take vp lodging without a briefe or billet from the Harbinger: for otherwiſe ſhuld appeare ſmal dutie or regard of the Officers, and among the principalleſt and chiefeſt ſouldiers, this rule ought firſt to be obſerued, for an apparaunt example to all the reſt, to the intent, vtterly to baniſh diſorder.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How and in what order a company of Hargu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſiers ought to enter into the Towne. Cap. 7.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the companie bée Hargubuſiers, they ſhall enter in this ſorte. Firſt, the Corſelettes ſhall bée placed in the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, with a Drumme player. And if the order be that they ſhall goe thrée in a Ranke, the Drumme player ſhall goe after the third Ranke. But if the order be by fiue and fiue, the Drum ſhall then goe after the fifth ranke, and then ſhall follow the Enſigne with another Drumme player and a Flute. But there muſt be a pretie ſpace betwéene the Corſelettes and the Hargubuſiers, by reaſon of the Enſigne, Drumme player, and Flute,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3721:7"/>
becauſe they muſt be placed betwéene the corſelets and hargubuſeirs, and the corſelets muſt each carrie an ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶If the companie be Pikemen, then muſt they obſerue this order in their entrie. Cap. 8.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N a companie of Pikemen, the hargu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſeiers ſhall march in their vangard with their drumme player in the ranke that he ſhall be appointed, in the ranke of thrée or fiue, and then ſhall march the Enſigne with the drumme player and Fluite: before the Pikemen ſhall march the corſlettes of the companie, and in the reregard the <hi>Cabos de ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> of Pikemen which ſhoulde be corſelets. And nowe muſt the companie of Pikemen goe in the reregarde or elſe the hargubuſeirs, the baggage of each ſhall go néere vnto the campe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶The order to be obſerued in going to the alonge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Cap. 9.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore the companie departe from the place where they are lodged, the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benger ſhal depart thrée or foure houres, or a whole daie before the armie, and haue made prouiſion of lodging before their comming. And then he ſhall yeeld or giue vnto the Sergeant, a briefe note according to the number that he hath in his memoriall to diuide them to their lodging.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How a companie ought to be lodged. Cap. 10.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3721:8"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He beſt Inne or lodging is to be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the Captaine, and the ſeconde is likewiſe to be giuen to the Auncient bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and Sergeant of the bande, next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them muſt be lodged the Drumme-plaiers and Fluite, &amp; then the Squadron of the Captaine, and after they are placed, muſt likewiſe be placed the ſquadron that is appointed for the garde or watch, and then thoſe that hath alreadye ſerued in that garde, and laſt of all the reſidue of the companie.</p>
                  <p>The Harbenger ought alwayes to take vp lodging for a greater number then is in his memoriall, not to the intent to benefit himſelfe, but rather that thereby maye remaine, and ſo be lodging for other poore trauay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>How the watch ought to be ſet. Cap. 11.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He companie béeing come to the lodge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Auntient-bearer in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der before they departe towarde theyr lodgeing, the garde or watch muſt bée warned to make them readye to attende that night on the Captaine, which watch muſt bée of the Captaines Squadron, and the nexte night following another Squadron of Hargubuſeires, and ſo conſequently all the other Squadrons.</p>
                  <p>And then muſt followe the Pikemen in the ſame order, and when euerye Squadron hath obſerued his courſe, then muſt they begin againe as at the firſt, ſo that they may alwaies kéepe a good order in their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching forward, and to be experimented in their duetifull ſeruice of their Prince.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3721:8"/>
                  <head>¶How their lodging ſhall be appointed for auoiding of briberie. Cap. 12.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Vigilant care muſt be had that no ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier haue appointed for him, more then his néedfull lodgeing, and therewith to content themſelues, bée it eyther for a ſpeciall or a perticular number. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that occaſion ſhould be auoyded of chopping and chaunging of lodging for intereſt or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and alſo oppreſſing the Cities, Townes, or Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges where they lye. The officers' muſt haue of this point a ſpeciall care, but principally the Captaine, his Liefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunt, or Enſigne-bearer, on whome the charge perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly lyeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <head>How the baggage ſhall returne. Cap. 13.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE baggage ſhall not bée tranſported from one place to another without great neceſſitie, becauſe one towne maye not bée more ouercharged then another. And when they ſhall retourne to the place where they were appointed, they ſhall yéelde account of their receiuing, to the intent that no Souldyer loyter behinde from one day to another, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times they vſe to doe, which is a greate diſorder, and the only fault lyeth in the officers that ought to haue care thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How poore husbandmen ought not to bee op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Cap. 14.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3721:9"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the whole companie are lodged, the officers appointed ought in the night ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to goe from houſe to houſe to knowe and vnderſtande of the behauiour of the Souldiers, to this effect, that the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunts be not moleſted or diſquieted by theyr companie, requiring impertinent, vnlawful, or more then is néedfull at theyr hoſts handes. This charge doth onely apperteine to the Enſigne bearer and Sergeaunt of the band. And the Captaine ought to haue regard to admoniſh thoſe Officers to looke to their charge, and ſée that it be obſerued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How the watch muſt be ſet, and the manner how to remoue the Scout. Cap. 15.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very night watch muſt bée kept as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie procéed on theyr iourney, becauſe when they happen to come amonge eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, they ſhalbée better willing through theyr former experience and practiſe, and alſo how they may knowe to appoint theyr ſcout, &amp; the ſame to chaunge at their houres, in ſuch ſort that thoſe which are of the firſt watch, maye call the ſecond at his time, and the ſecond the third, vnto the fourth, one giuing aduiſe to another with the watch word, that the Sergeaunt ſhall giue them, kéeping the ſame in great ſecrecie, but the watch word the Sergeant muſt haue at the mouth of the Captaine, or his Liefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunt in his abſence. In the Summer ſeaſon they vſe to diuide the watch into thrée partes of the night, and in the winter into fowre. But this order is reſerued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that hath the whole charge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How the watch muſt be choſen. Cap. 16.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3721:9"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne Watch muſt call another, as hath bene already declared, ſo that the Sarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant may not be ouer troubled with that charge, at the leaſt not being in place of daunger of enimies. Yet neuertheleſſe, he is not to be excuſed from often viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Watch, by meane whereof, he may haue bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderſtanding to know ſuch Souldiers, as hée may beſt truſt in time of neceſſitie. In the morning the bodie of the Gard or Watch ſhall come abroad with ſound of Drum, by order accuſtomed, if there be no cauſe to the contrarie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How the Watch muſt be charged or ſet, and where they meete or repaire together. Cap. 17.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Watch muſt be charged at the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, &amp; ioyne together at the dore, wher the <hi>Cabo de Squadra</hi> lieth, that hath the charge or lot to watch that night. And if it happen to be the Captaines Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, then ſhall the Watch méete at the Sargeants lodging. Sometimes the Enſigne bearer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth into his lot of watching: But it is no ordinarye thing, becauſe it is the office of the Sergeant.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How lodging ought to be demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Cap. 18.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Harbinger in prouiding of the alodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie, ought to ioine with the Ruler &amp; other Officers of the Citie or Towne, where the Armie ſhoulde bée lodged, &amp; to demaund of them the bookes of Subſidie or other taſkes paide by the Communaltie of that place, to the intent, that euery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant
<pb facs="tcp:3721:10"/>
or huſbandman may ſupply according to theyr abilitie, and not to burden the poore, and let the rich eſcape frée.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How the Frutes, Vines, and Orchardes, ought to be kept from the ſpoiling of the souldiers. Cap. 19.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen it ſhoulde happen a companye to march, néere vnto any place, where are Vines, Orchards, or any kinde of fruits, wherein Souldiers might doe any hurte: The Captain or Enſigne bearer ought to be aduertiſed of ſuch place or places, before their departure from their alodgment: becauſe before the company come to that place they ſtay all together, &amp; then to march ioyntly together, and that a <hi>Cabo de Squadra</hi> with certaine Souldiers be ſent before, to gard the place where hurt might be. For if this order were not, great ſpoyle would be made by vnruly perſons in poore mens ground.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="chapter">
                  <head>How euerie Souldier ought to content himſelfe, with the lodging that is allotted for him. Cap. 20.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the company is lodged in any place wher they paſſe, proclamation muſt be made, how the Captaine commaundeth on great penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that no Souldier preſume to abuſe by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meanes his Hoſte, Hoſteſſe or Familye, and that they content themſelues with ſuch things, as ſhall be giuen them, without conſtraining or compelling them to any more. And that it is the Captaines will, that if any man can iuſtly complaine of any Souldier of that companie, he maye ſafely come to the Captaine to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3721:10"/>
complaine, &amp; they ſhall be heard, &amp; the offender puniſhed.</p>
                  <p>This order muſt be obſerued, when one companye or many marcheth by themſelues.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How a diſcord ſhoulde bee pacified, if anye happen betweene a company of ſouldiers, and the Townes men. Cap. 21.</head>
                  <p>WHen any Towne chance to fall at ſtrife, with a company of Souldiers that are lodged in their Towne, and the diſcord chaunce to grow about or for want of lodging, which oftentimes doeth happen, the Captaine ought to proclaime, that all his Souldiers foorthwith repaire to his Enſigne, whether they be armed or vnarmed, vpon good conſideration there to attend and doe the thing that ſhall be neceſſarye and conuenient, to the ſeruice of their Prince, and in this ſort to pacifie their contention with great foreſight, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that all ſuch alterations are againſt the Princes ſeruice, and being gathered and come together, they ſhall retire by the Captaines commaundement to the place that vnto him ſhall ſéeme conuenient, for their greater quietneſſe and pacification. For otherwiſe the broile would not be ended, without great hurt of both parties.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶Of the order that ought to be obſerued, to ſuch effect that the companies maye be alwaies prepared in a readineſſe to make a squadron, and where both Pike men and Hargubuſiers ought to be placed. cap. 22.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rmour and weapon being deliuered to each ſouldier of a company, whether it be at going on ſhipboord, or otherwiſe wher they ſhalbe receiued. To euery company ſhalbe appointed one part of Hargubu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiers, and two of Pike men, and if
<pb facs="tcp:3721:11"/>
there be any want, it ſhall appeare by the generall mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and copie of the number of them, and being founde not equall in order, the Hargubuſiers that were more then néede, muſt be taken and placed where the want is, and the lyke among the Pike men. This account ought euerie Captaine to obſerue among his companye, ſo that in this wiſe they ſhall be to moſt purpoſe in ſeruice. And euen ſo the Generall ought to giue commaundement to the Campe maſters in theyr ſtéede, to whom the charge doth appertaine in thirdes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3721:11"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART, <hi>De re militari.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="23" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶Of the companies of Hargubuſires which ſhall bee needfull in euerye third. Cap. 23.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N an hoaſt or armie that is to be ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the companies ought to bée diuided into thirds, becauſe they may vnderſtand to what partie they may repaire, and in euery tierce or third, there ſhould be two companies of hargubuſires, beſides thoſe which are reſited for a third, of the companies of Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the which ſhall ſerue in diuerſe ſortes, as ſomtimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o runne the fielde, and other whiles to take victualles from the enimie, alſo to defend or kéepe paſſages, as brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or riuers, kéeping them to theyr vſe and fafetie: alſo to Skirmiſh, giue Camiſada, lye in Ambuſh, to kéepe watch in the day ſeaſon, at the Gates of Cities, or other places that ought to bée garded, and for all manner of ſeruice néedfull, which is not conueniet to the companies of Pikemen, nor yet may not be ſerued of them, as well for mountaines, ſtraight paſſages, and other difficult pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe Piks are troubleſome and cannot be in ſuch places ſo manuable, as ſpéede and agilitie requireth, as Hargubuſiers, who may enter into Squadron alwaias, not hauing other ſeruice wherein to be employed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3721:12"/>
                  <head>Of the wayes and manner that ſome hath writ to ordeine a Squadron. Cap. 24.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome Captaines and men experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the warres haue written ſundrye wayes differing one from another in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyning a Squadron. And after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deining thereof, they haue not liked the ſtile, or found the ſame profitable. As for example, ſome vſe Triangle wiſe, ſome Croſſe wiſe, and ſome in a round or ring, the which moſt men cannot bring to paſſe except the number were few, likewiſe they cannot march or auaile themſelues, but onely being firme, for if they would otherwiſe march, of force they muſt goe out of order, according as they haue written, and I my ſelfe haue ſéene by the authours of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="chapter">
                  <head>How they may be ordered touching their weapons. Cap. 25.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is ſome wayes to ordeine a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron in ſquare, which is, when it doth concerne one ſort of weaponne, which then muſt march in rowe, when the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes commeth to the Artillerie, or to the place which ſhoulde bée aſſigned to them in order, according to the number of the rowe, and the diſpoſition of the place or ground, where they ſhould ioyne with the Souldiers, being few or many that eache Enſigne hath, or each Captaine had gathered together, without any delay of the Enſigne bearer. They ought to haue ſuch ſouldiers in their companie that ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent at all times to attend and repaire to the Enſigne,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3721:12"/>
for to goe vnto ſuch place as they ſhall be commaunded to repaire vnto. And as the ſouldiers come gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to their Enſignes, then ſhall they procéed on row, ſo many on a rowe, as their account or reckoning doth ſpecifie. The chiefe ſergeant according to his number of ſoldiers which he hath, at which inſtant it is not to haue regard to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vangard doth apperteine, neither maine battell, or reregard of euery terme nor companie. For at the time of neceſſitie they cannot be ordeined to aſſigne, or giue that which vnto euerye third or companye doth count the ſame day. In this forme or manner none ſhalbe agréeued, becauſe the thing may not otherwiſe be done by reaſon of the damage or diſorder that might enſue, in the delay, ſo that in the ſame manner as they go ioyning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, euen in the ſame forme, they ſhall go ordaining the rowes, and hauing time, there ſhall be giuen to each tierce or company, that which perteineth vnto them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vangard, maine battell, or reregard. The enimies not being ſo nigh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the order may be kept as is declared.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="chapter">
                  <head>The manner how the Tudeſcos ordeined their Quadrant. Cap. 26.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He nation or people called <hi>Tudeſcos</hi> vſed to ordeine their manner of Quadrant as followeth. As they went gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their Enſignes according to the number which ſhould be ſet in order, vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding how many perteined to a rank, but whileſt the ranke was not equall according to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, they abide in forme of a bow, which doth ſignifie that the ranks are not furniſhed. And this foreſight or account had the firſt men that came to the Enſigne, &amp; when the ranks were repleat or full, they ſtaide: &amp; euen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame manner, the reſidue or others that came afterward to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their Quadrant, vntill they were fully repleate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3721:13"/>But this ſéemeth not vnto me a good ſtile or vſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the truſt was repoſed in the order of the firſt that ioined together, without conſideration whether they wer men expert, or no: notwithſtanding the ordeining of a Quadrant ought to bée done by the officers, which for that purpoſe ſhould be appointed, for otherwiſe it ſhould be a diſorder.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="chapter">
                  <head>Of the difficultie that is in the foreſayd manner of order. Cap. 27.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is another manner of ordayning in the number of fiue or, ſeauen, more or leſſe, which is, that they muſt go dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the rankes in this wiſe. That is to ſaye, to place the ſecond rowe in the firſt of the Vangarde, and the fourth in the ſeconde place, and the ſixt in the third, and in this ſort to ordaine all the reſt, til the number be finiſhed. And doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling once, muſt redouble againe, vntill the number bée equall, to make a Quadrant according to the account of number that is kept of the infanterie or footmen.</p>
                  <p>The Enſignes and Drumme players ſhall goe at or in the ranke, that the number requireth, which héereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall more plainely bée declared according, and of the manner, as néede ſhall require, where the ſame ſhall be ordeined.</p>
                  <p>But when occaſion ſhall ſerue to double and redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ranks, as often as the number is conuenient, there is found two inconueniences.</p>
                  <p>The one is, for to double a ranke, they go diuiding, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a great and voide place or ſpaces betwéene the one ranke and the other, ſo that they ſhould run with ſpéed to reach vnto the ranke that marcheth, into the which they ſhould enter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3721:13"/>And in this wiſe if at that inſtant they ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered, they goe in great daunger to be loſt, becauſe they goe wandering out of order. Beſides this, there is another inconuenience in the manner of ordaining in doubling and redoubling, which bringeth the number vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to order. And forſomuch, that this thing may be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, it is on this ſorte. That if a number of Souldiers amount to 400. being ordained by fiue and fiue, doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the rankes once, from the ſecond to the firſt,, &amp; from the fourth to the third, till the number be finiſhed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining 10. in a ranke, ſo that in this lyttle number of 400. men, is to be vnderſtood the like in a greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. But redoubling againe which is the ſecond order, and ſhall remaine by 20. and 20. for front ſide and reregarde, which for the number of 400. is well ordained, becauſe there doth remayne by 20. and 20. for Front ſide and Reregarde. But if the Souldiers were 300. in number, this ſhould not be a good way of ordenaunce, for if they deale but onely once in ranke it ſhall remaine euill or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, becauſe the Front ſhall be too little, and the ſides ouer large, and euen ſo being redoubled, it ſhall be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in front then large in quantitie, and ſo ſhall remayne euill ordered.</p>
                  <p>And if the Souldiours were 600. it ſhoulde be the like, but to ordaine of this ſort, the number ought to bée equall to come vnto reaſon. And not being equall, ſhuld be to ordaine of an euil ſtile, beſide the ſpaces which ſhuld be made, as hath bene declared.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶Of the account or care, that the chiefe Sergeant ought to haue, that the thing maye bee well ordeyned. Cap. 28.</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                        <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3721:14"/>
of the Battaile, the Pikes of the Companies of the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and after the bare Pikes of the companies of the Vangard, the Pikes of the Companies of the Battayle, And after the Pikes of the companies of the battayle, muſt follow the Pikes of the Companies of the Rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and after the Pikes of the Reregard muſt followe the Corſelets of the Companies of the Reregard. And in this ſort ſhall be giuen to euery Company, or companyes the Vangarde, Battaile or Reregard, when their turne falleth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶Of the order that doth appertaine to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie or companies of Vangarde, Battaile, or Reregard. Cap. 32.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the Tierces or Companies of Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, Battaile or Reregard, doth apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to haue conſideration, that to thoſe that were one daye of the Vangard doth belong the next daye the Reregard, and vnto them that were of the Reregarde this daye, to morrow doth appertaine the Battaile, and in this ſort ſhall they march from daye to daye, or in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Squadron, ſo that in this wiſe no tierce ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauiated. And the ſelfe ſame order that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sergeant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior ſhall kéepe in all the Tierces, which by him ſhall be ordained, the other Sergeants ſhall kéepe among theyr Companye perticularly. For when they ſhall ordayne, they may knowe the place, that vnto each Companye doth appertaine, either of Vangard or Battaile.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How it is not a thing vnmeete, for the footmen to march in Tierces. Cap. 33.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3721:14"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome will ſay that it is a great incoueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to march in tierces, of whom ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons are to be made in place where the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nimie is at hande: becauſe it ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that they goe out of order, forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that euerie Squadron, that ſhould be, goeth in tierce and not full, wherefore if in caſe the contraries ſhould come and finde them out of order. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinly by this meane coulde not come anie preiudice or hurt, but rather profit. For if the contrarie commeth in Squadron, they cannot ſo ſoone ouertake the infanterye called Footmen, which go in tierces, becauſe they haue no place to ordeine them. And if he would ouertake &amp; make haſt, yet ſhall they ſtray out of order, &amp; comming in ſuch ſort, any of the tierces may reſiſt them and put them to the diſorder, although the Squadron be not formed. And he that were in ſuch ſort ſet vpon, might thinke himſelfe happie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="chapter">
                  <head>Of the manner and order, and in what place the Enſigne ſhall goe. Cap. 34.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt now returning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe, to make an end to ordeine our Squadron after the laſt manner. The Enſigne ſhould bée placed in the firſt tierce of the Pikes on this wiſe, if they be .45. on a ranke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes goe in the 15. ranke, and the ſame order ſhall be kept both in the great and ſmall number.</p>
                  <p>Before the tierces ioyne, euery Sergeant ſhall place his Enſigne, according to the account perticular, ſo that they may all fall in ranke after the Squadron is ordeined.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="chapter">
                  <head>Of the manner how euery Tierce ſhould be ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by it ſelfe. Cap. 35.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3721:15"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F euerie tierce ſhould be made a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, and alſo béeing diſpoſed to make of foot men two or thrée Squadrons. Then each ſhoulde be ordained by himſelfe by the ſame order y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may go according to the reckoning a fore ſayde to make a Squadron diuiding them before they ioyne in tierces.</p>
                  <p>And if of the whole number a Squadron ſhould bée made, alone ought euerie tierce to come in order, on this wiſe, wating thrée partes of the foot men ſide wiſe, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e part of the third, forefront, taking out the Hargu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ers of euery tierce, for to place the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again at their due time, ſo that this order ought to be kept as well in great number as in ſmal, ſo that the ioyning of the tierces may be equall both by ſides and reregard, and in this ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ete al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they goe marching<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, or abide firme or ſtill in a place, if they ſhould be diſpoſed to forme the Quadrant. Then ſhall the tierce of the vangard ſtay, and the tierce of the battell ſhall march on the one ſide, and the tierce of the reregard on the other ſide, and in this wiſe ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ordenied. And the Enſignes ſhall bée placed in one of the ranks, according to the reckoning as hath ben de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, in much or little quantitie of Souldiers. But it ſhall be neceſſarie that when the tierce of the Vangard ſtayeth, and the tierce of the battell marcheth on the one ſide, and the reregard on the other ſide with the Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant maior, and minors vnto whom that daye the order doth belong. That then the Captaines which ſhall bee found in the vangard as the tearces doth approch, they ſhall goe ordeining the firſt ranks as they come &amp; ioyne them with this of the vangard which are already in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And the Sergeant or Sergeant maiors ſhall ſtande néere to the ranke where the Enſignes are placed, to haue ſpeciall care that there paſſe no more ranks of the tier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces then thoſe which were appointed in the tierce of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3721:15"/>
vangard. And likewiſe they ſhall cauſe to ſtay the reſidue that commeth, as vnto the acceant doth apperteine.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt ranke which ſtandeth behind the Enſignes they ſhall march eache in order without excéeding the one, nor wanting the other, for if any ranke ſhould ſober or want of thoſe which ought to paſſe of the Enſignes vntill the vangard, the errour ſhould be euill to mend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe of that tierce ſhould returne backe againe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring to ſéeke the rank in the which each ſhuld reforme. And likewiſe ſhould remaine perticularly ſome officers in the reregard, and ſhuld put in order the laſt ranks of that tierce, cauſing euery one to abide in the place which to him or them belongeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="chapter">
                  <head>Of the order which ought to be obſerued if any Souldiers ſobre at the ioyning of the rankes. Cap. 36.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F at the ioyning of the cohorts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called companies of foote men, there ſober ſome Souldiers of the tierces, ſo that they may not march equall, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that it is ordinary to ſover in one ranke or other. Then the Sergeant ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior with diligence, if among ſuch be a ranke, with ſpéed ſhall put them in order and they amount to more then one ranke he ſhall doe the like, and if there be not inough to make a ranke, he ſhall place, one, two, or m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſouldiers in the ranks that vnto him ſhall ſéeme conuenient, where moſt néed ſhall require, vntill they be all placed, and ſo ſhall they be well ordeined. But this muſt be done before the Squadron be garniſhed of Hargubuſiers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶The order how the Hargubuſiers ſhall iſſue out from among the Pikemen, before they begin to ordeine. Cap. 37.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3721:16"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore the tierce of Pike men begin to be ſet in order, the Sergeant maior of euery Tierce ſhall command each tierce that ſhould be ordeined by it ſelfe. That all the Hargubuſeirs iſſue out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Pikemen round about them, by that part where moſt ſpace ſhall be found, after the Captaine or Captains of Hargubuſeirs, which vnto each apperteyneth. The which Captaines with the Hargubu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeirs of their companye, and with the reſt that were of the companyes of Pikemen that ſhoulde be ordeined in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſquadron. They ſhall march following their Captains in order by thrêe or fiue in ranke, according to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that is among them. And in the meane while that the Hargubuſeirs doth march and giue a turne, the Sergeant ſhall ordeine by their Tierce the Pikemen, by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in eache ranke that the Sergeant maior hath appointed. And hauing ioyned the Tierces as is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the Hargubuſeirs ſhall enter Front vnto Front of the Squadron by the leaſt ſide, and ſo ſhall giue a turne by the reregard, following alwayes after theyr Captaine or Captaines, and ſo ſhall procéede and march on vnto the Vangard of the right ſide. So that in this ſort the Squadron ſhall remaine garniſhed by both ſides and reregard in good order.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How the Hargubuſiers ſhall be diuided if they be not needfull in the rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. Cap. 35.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3721:16"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing no néede of Hargubuſiers for the Reregard, the number may be employed in this wiſe: If the company be ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by fiue in Ranke, vnto them and each ranke maye bée added two, ſo that the Ranke be vij. and if they be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that all the Hargubuſiers remaine ouerplus, which did belong to the Reregard, then the Hargubuſiers ſhall goe in the firſt order, and the ouerplus may haue the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by diuiding into the place, where beſt occaſion ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and alſo in placing them where they déeme or think the Enimie to come, or at the leaſt to diſcouer with them the want of Horſemen, or to diſcouer an ambuſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How the Enſignes of the Campe Maiſters, ſhall march. Cap. 39.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Enſignes of the Campe Maiſters, which were in the tierce or Tierces, ſhal march in this order: If there be but one alone, in one onely Tierce, he ſhall goe at the point of the right hand, &amp; if there were two Tierces of two Campe Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the one ſhall goe on the right hande, and the other on the left hand, becauſe they are places of moſt honour, and moſt daunger. And if the Squadron were great, the halfe of the Enſignes ſhall goe on the right ſide, and the other on the left ſide, chaunging euery daye by the order that hath bene declared, in the many or few that were, &amp; ſo doing, there ſhall be no diuiſion at the time of orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and none ſhall be aggrauated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3721:17"/>
                  <head>¶How the baggage or carriage ſhall march in time of enimies, and how they ſhall march when there is no daunger. Cap. 40.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Arching, the Squadron or Squadrons ordained, the baggage ſhall goe by the Tierces on this wiſe. If the Enimie chaunce to come on the Vangarde, the Baggage ſhall goe in the Reregarde of euery Tierce, vnto whom it doth apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and a company of Hargabuſiers, ſhall attende for their garde, or two companies, if the baggage belong to two tierces, the which ſhall march in ſight of the tier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Reregard.</p>
                  <p>And if the Enimie happen to come on the Reregard, the baggage ſhall paſſe to the Vangard with their garde or company of Hargubuſiers, in ſuch order that they may ſuccour when néede requireth, not departing or ſeuering from the Vangard or Reregard, whereas they were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to goe. And hauing no enimies, they ſhall go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tierce or tierces of the battaile and the reregard. This order ſhall be in marching, and ſhall be done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diſpoſition of the Countrey wheras they march, and the manner thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How a Squadron ſhould be inlarged or ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after the ordaining thereof. Cap. 41.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F a Squadron ſhould be made greater be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a greater number then héere is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, hauing more footemen, and alſo to be made of greater ſide then front through the diſpoſition of the place, the Rankes of each tierce ſhall diminiſh in leſſe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that they may come iuſt to the account that hath ben
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3721:17"/>
declared to be ordained in the firſt perfection.</p>
                  <p>And if there ſhould come as many mee footmen, and to ioyne all in one, the Hargubuſiers ſhould be taken out of the one part, &amp; the footmen put in order, that ſhal enter into the third part of ſouldiers that the Squadron hath in Ranke, making therof two companies, the one ſhal joine to the one ſide, and the other companye ſhall enter into the Reregard, croſſing from the one poynt to the other. The which ſhall haue moe rankes then the firſt confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie that the number hath in as many as were in rank ordained, and doing ſo they ſhall remaine in the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and according to the reckoning that was firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted.</p>
                  <p>If the halfe of thoſe which were ordayned come to ſuccour, then ſhall they put in Ranke the firſt parte of ſuch as are in Squadron, and ſo ſhall they come well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and in the ſame forme, as they were at the firſt. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cohorts being put with the Pikemen as hath ben declared, the Hargubuſiers that come to ſuccour ſhall be gathered with thoſe that were firſt put in order, and ſhall then retourne to round the Squadron, increaſing or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in the order that they ſhuld enter, by the account and number that the one haue of the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How the Squadron beeing ſo ordained on all partes maye make both Vangard and Rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. Cap. 42.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow the ſquadron being ordained, by the forme and account alredy ſpecified, of the ſides may be made vangard, &amp; of the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard &amp; reregard, right ſide, and left ſide, and on what ſide ſo euer that they ſhuld bée ſette on, they maye make Fronte
<pb facs="tcp:3721:18"/>
of Vangard, they may alſo march, ſet on, breake, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, onely it ſhall be néedfull to chaunge the Enſignes on that ſide where the Vangarde is planted for to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the account of the Rankes which were firſt. And this is, becauſe it may not be vnderſtood, if a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron ſhould come to aſſault on any ſide, that they ſhoulde goe round about for to turne to the Vangard, conſidering there is no neceſſitie of other thing, but for the footemen to turne their face to the part where they ſhould bée en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered, or ſet vpon, or would encounter, and ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ordained with the ſame force as it was at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſithens the order abideth on the ſame manner. But to goe round about ſhould be a great diſorder.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How few in number ſhould be ſet in order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt many. Cap. 43.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the Enimies were moe then the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron which ſhould breake with them, ſo manye ſouldiers ſhoulde be ordained in Ranke as they may get, ſo that they may not girdle them in front on the part of the ſides, for the vantage ſhould be much, and the daunger greater, conſidering, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fortune or waight of the matter dependeth in the firſt fiue or ſixe Rankes, &amp; if it happen the Enemie ſéeing ſo great a Front in the Squadron which he helde for ſo ſmall, they would ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that ſome ſuccour or ayde were come, which ſhould be an occaſion ſomewhat to diſcourage them hauing iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them for many leſſe, then thoſe that the order did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="chapter">
                  <head>¶How vigilant care is to bee had, in giuing the onſet, whether the Souldiers are willing or vnwilling. Cap. 44.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:3721:18"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is neceſſarie, that a battayle hauing order to be giuen, the Souldiers ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues either willing or time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and without hope to obteine vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, the which in their countenaunce or apperaunce may appeare, after that they are ſet in order. This foreſight or knowledge doth appertaine to the generall of the Hoaſt, and campe mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which were knowne to be moſt expert, and to giue great charge vnto the Sergeants maiors, that they maye ſée and conſider what they ought to do, according to their knowledge.</p>
                  <p>And the waight of the matter béeing found not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenient tearme for the purpoſe. The giuing of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle ought to bée excuſed, béeing in his hand at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant which was appointed. And dooing ſo it ſhall bée well done, either to giue them preſent pay, or elſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe it them, and to content and pleaſe them in all their deſire.</p>
                  <p>But if of force the battaile muſt be giuen. Then it ſhall bée néedfull to encourage them, and to giue them to vnderſtand, that the victory is certeine and ſure on their ſide, truſting vnder God in their ſtrength and valour, repreſenting vnto them the lyke things and ſucceſſes that hath happened in lyke ſorte, and this muſt bée de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared vnto them according to the wiſdome and courage of him that hath the charge to gouerne them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="chapter">
                  <head>Of the manner that the Hargubuſiers ſhould iſſue out of the Squadron to skirmiſh. Cap. 45.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3721:19"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the Hargubuſiers ſhuld come to ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh béeing in the Squadron, it ſhall be on this wiſe. The one ſléeue or wing of the one ſide, on that part where they ſhall giue the onſet, or elſe be ſet vppon ſhall begin to diſcharge the ſhot, hauing eare the one to the other, kéeping time in the diſcharge as ſhall appeare moſt néedfull, and before the ſhot make an ende the Captaine or Sergeant which was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for that purpoſe ſhall regather his companie. And then ſhall iſſue out the ſléeue or wing on the other ſide, to receiue thoſe that retyreth without hurt, to haue them prepared in readineſſe for the ſkirmiſhe, and when thoſe that iſſued out firſt haue retired, then ſhall the ſecond go out to doe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like, and then the third in order, ſtaieng one for the other. So that whileſt the one ſhotte, the other ſhould retire, &amp; in this order they ſhall be able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine themſelues with continuall ſhot vntil they be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded otherwiſe all in good order.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="chapter">
                  <head>Of the order how to put a ſunder or vndoe a Squadron that ſhould be lodged. Cap. 46.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Squadron hauing no néede to remaine in forme, &amp; béeing in tearme to be lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, according as time giueth place, they ſhall come out in this wiſe. The Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the Hargubuſiers ſhal march by the ſame order as they entered in, or their Liefetenaunt in their ſtéede, following them all the Hargubuſiers, and then euerye tierce by himſelfe, their Enſignes ioyne together, as in the ſame tierce was ordeined, accounting them their Souldiers which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine vnto them. And then ſhall euery Enſigne ſtande
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3721:19"/>
aſide in his due place, and the ſouldiers of euery compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to follow their Enſigne, and euen in the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall the Hargubuſiers follow their Enſignes, after that they are out of the Squadron, and then to take theyr lodging, according to the appointment of the order of the Officers.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>The end of the ſecond part.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3721:20"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>THE THIRD PART, <hi>De re militari.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="47" type="chapter">
                  <head>How it is needfull to haue account among the Pike-men &amp; Hargubuſiers to make a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron. Cap. 47.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eere before hath béene declared the order how to plant a Squadron to march well ordained, and the difficultie to ordaine. Now it is néedfull according to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Hargubuſiers or Pike-men that in euery of the Squadrons ſhould be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined, to haue account of the number that were, of how many commeth in ranke, from the number of 500. foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with Pikes, vnto the number of 3000. and the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gubuſiers that were néedfull for that number to be gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the ſides and reregard as before hath bene decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, hauing one tierce of Hargubuſiers and two of pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſome more or leſſe according to the order as is declared, who ſhal not let to enter into the number of the reckoning that goeth before, conſidering that they may reach to the mo, and to the leſſe, and may not want many, nor yet ſober by the third part ſpecified. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies being referred vnto them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3721:20"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>IF the Squadron were of fiue hundred twentie and nine Pike men, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth to a Ranke. 23.</cell>
                           <cell>23</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>If there were two hundred and ſeauen Hargubuſiers, to girdle the Pikemen both by ſides and reregard, they ſhall march by 3. and .3.</cell>
                           <cell>207</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har.</cell>
                           <cell>If they were thrée hundred fortie and fiue, they ſhall march fiue on a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>345</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this order the Sergeant Maior ſhall ſet them in order, and the Captaine commaund the ſame order to be obſerued, or his Lieutenant, and ſo ſhall they come well ordayned according to the Squadron.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Squadron were of ſixe hundred twentie and fiue Pike men, they ſhall be twentie and fiue on a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>25</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred twentie and fiue, they ſhall march by 3. and 3.</cell>
                           <cell>225</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were thrée hundred twentie &amp; fiue, then ſhall they march by fiue and fiue on Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>325</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Squadron were of ſeauen hundred thirtie and nine Pike men, then doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long 27. to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>27</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3721:21"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers which ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Squadron, were two hundred for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and thrée, then ſhall they march by 3. and .3.</cell>
                           <cell>243</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were foure hundred twentie and fiue, then ſhall they march by fiue on a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>425</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Squadron were of eyght hundred fortie and one Pike men, then belongeth 29. to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>29</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſixtie and one, then ſhall they march by 3. and 3.</cell>
                           <cell>261</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were foure hundred thyrtie &amp; fiue, they ſhall then marche by fiue and fiue.</cell>
                           <cell>435</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Squadron were of nine hundred ſixtie and one Pike men, then belongeth thirtie one to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>31</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſeuentie nine, they ſhall march in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by 3. and .3.</cell>
                           <cell>279</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were foure hundred lxx.v. they ſhall march by fiue on ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>475</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Squadron were of one thouſande eight hundred and nine Pike men, then belongeth to a Ranke .33.</cell>
                           <cell>33</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3721:21"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ninetie and fiue, there appertayneth 3. to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>295</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were foure hundred ninetie and fiue, then ſhall they march by fiue on a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>495</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Squadron were of one thouſande two hundred twentie and fiue, then belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth 35. to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>35</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were 325. they ſhall march by 3. on a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>325</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were fiue hundred twentie and fiue, then ſhall they march by fiue on Ranke, and kéepe good order.</cell>
                           <cell>525</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Squadron were of one thouſande thrée hundred ſixtie and nine, then belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth 37. to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>37</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thirtie thrée, they ſhall enter by thrée into a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>333</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were fiue hundred fiftie and fiue, they ſhall marche by fiue and fiue.</cell>
                           <cell>555</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Squadron were a thouſande fiue hundred twentie and one Pike men, then belongeth 39. to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>39</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3721:22"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fiftie and one, they muſt march by 3. on Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>351</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were fiue hundred eyghtie and fiue, then ſhall they goe by fiue in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</cell>
                           <cell>585</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If a Squadron of Pikemen were in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber one thouſand ſix hundred eightie one, then belongeth 41. to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>41</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were 369. they ſhall be 3. on Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>369</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were 615. then ſhall the order be fiue on Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>615</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Pike men were one thouſand eight hundred fortie nine, then belongeth 43. to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>43</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were 387. they ſhall march by 3. and 3.</cell>
                           <cell>387</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were ſixe hundred fortie and fiue, then ſhall they march by fiue on Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>645</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Pike men were in number two thouſand twentie fiue, then belongeth 45. to a Ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>45</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fiue in number, then ſhall they march by .3.</cell>
                           <cell>405</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:3721:22"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were ſixe hundred lxxv. they muſt march by fiue on a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>675.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Squadron of Pike men in number two thouſand, two hundred and nine, then apperteineth 47. to a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>47.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred twentie and thrée, they muſt march by 3.</cell>
                           <cell>423</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were in number ſeauen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fiue, they ſhall march fiue on a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>705.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the ſquadron were in number two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand foure hundred and one, then belongeth 49. to a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>49</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred xli. then ſhall march thrée on a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>441</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were ſeauen hundred thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and fiue, then belongeth fiue to a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>735.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Pike men were two thouſand ſixe hundred, and one, then belongeth 51. to a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>51.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers wer foure hundred lix. they ſhall march by thrée on a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>459</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were in number ſeuen hundred lxv. then ſhall enter fiue in a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>765</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3721:23"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the were Pike men in number two thouſande, viii. hundred and nine, then liii. belongeth to a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>53</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred lxxvii. they ſhall march by thrée on ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>477</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were ſeauen hundred lxxxx. &amp; fiue in number, then ſhall enter fiue into a ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>795</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pi.</cell>
                           <cell>If the Pike men were in number 3. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand twentie and fiue, then muſt 55. enter into ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>55</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 3</cell>
                           <cell>And if the Hargubuſiers were foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred lxxxxv. then ſhal thrée enter inot rank.</cell>
                           <cell>495</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Har. 5</cell>
                           <cell>And if they were eight hundred twentie fiue in number, then muſt they march by fiue on ranke.</cell>
                           <cell>825</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the lyke as well in the former number as in the reſt muſt be obſerued, and by the ſame order the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron may be roome both by ſides and reregard.</p>
                  <p>In this number of Pike men &amp; Hargubuſiers which in the reaſon &amp; account hath ben declared, and comming iuſt therewith the thing ſhould be perfect, &amp; the ſquadron wel ordeined. But although ther wer fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d more or leſſe in ſmal quantity, they diſturb not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order, nor yet therfore ſhall it let to be of purpoſe for to ſerue. And becauſe by theſe rules it may be the better vnderſtood, &amp; the Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant maior thereof auaile himſelfe, ioyning the number to the nigheſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3721:23"/>
                  <head>How the victuals ſhould be diſtributed. Cap. 50.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N an hoaſt or armie although they bée of ſundrie nations, béeing in campe &amp; in neceſſitie to be prouided with victualls of the Princes puruaiour general, or of ſuch perſon or perſons as for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe were appointed, this order ought to be obſerued, proclamation generall muſt be made, to the intent that all the officers vnto whome doth apperteine the charge to prouide for each nation, repaire to the place of diſtribution. And euerye nation hauing receiued his due part, proclamation muſt likewiſe be made among each nation, that the ſame prouiſion may be equallye di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to the tierce of euery campe maiſter, and to all other tierces by their companies, and of the companies by the <hi>Cabos de ſquadras,</hi> the number being knowne that euery of them hath, and from them to each perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar companie called a meſſe or <hi>Camaſada.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The lyke order muſt be obſerued in all kinde of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion that ſhoulde be diuided being neceſſarye for the warres, as well of Biſkuit, ſalt meates, Chéeſe, Wine, &amp; fiſh, as alſo of all other kinde of victuals y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be diſtributed, and in the ſame manner, Gunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, Lead, Pellets, Baſkets, ſhouells, Pikes, Pike-axes, and other neceſſaryes for the ſeruice of the Prince, that doth apperteine méet and conuenient to ſuch a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: prouided alwayes, that the firſt diſtribution ought to bée amonge the forreine Nations, by the Tierces of euerye Nation, and of the Tierces for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyes, and from the Companyes by the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dronnes, and by the Squadronnes to the Meſſes,
<pb facs="tcp:3721:24"/>
and by them to euery ſouldier, giuing alwaies the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to the Captaines, Enſigne bearers, and other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and ſouldiers to whom it were due.</p>
                  <p>I doe well vnderſtand that if it were not to ſuch as were affectioned to the exerciſe of armes, this ſmall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe would giue but ſmall delyght, but rather will reiect it as a thing vnprofitable, hauing no reſpect but onely to their paſtime. But I for my part cannot giue vnto them any other aduiſe, but onely ſuch as I haue learned in this art. And if the ſtile of procéeding ſhall ſéeme rude vnto them, yet I pray them to diſſemble it. For our office is more to giue order how to worke with weapon, and to ordeine infanterie or footemen, then eloquently to write with pen: yet there are wittes I doe knowe which want not eloquence in ſpeaking lyke Oratours, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent courage in fight like ſouldiers. The works of the which as well paſt as preſent are manifeſt for their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall memorie, without neceſſitie of other phraſe more then their publike fame hath proclaimed.</p>
                  <p>And if any errour haue eſcaped in this treatiſe touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Art héerein ſpecified, I heartely praye vnto him that vnderſtandeth it to aduertiſe me thereof, and I ſhall be alwayes readie to amend the ſame, conſidering that we ſée mans wit and iudgement how often and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie times it doth erre, &amp; alſo how there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this lyfe ſo perfect and pure, but that ſome defect may bée put thereto.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Imprinted at London by Thomas Eaſt. 1582.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3721:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
